Association on American Indian Affairs Records, 1851-2016 (bulk 1922-1995): Finding Aid MC147
Public Policy Papers
- Series 3: Personal Files, 1927-1991; 28 boxes
  - Subseries 1: Henry S. Forbes, 1954-1981; 6 boxes
    - Tundra Times, 1964-1968; 1971-1981; 6 folders (Box 386, Folder 1-6)
    - Tyonek, 1962-1966; 1 folder (Box 386, Folder 7)
    - VanStone, James, 1963-1964; 1 folder (Box 386, Folder 8)
    - Vietnam, 1968; 1 folder (Box 386, Folder 9)
    - Whale Gun, 1961-1965; 1 folder (Box 386, Folder 10)
    - Williamson, Thames W, 1957-1962; 1 folder (Box 386, Folder 11)
    - Wortis, Ethel, 1967; 1 folder (Box 386, Folder 12)
    - Photographs, 1961-1966; 1 box (Box 387)
  - Subseries 2: Hildegarde B. Forbes, 1927-1991; 13 boxes
    Series 3: Personal Files, Subseries 2: Hildegarde B. Forbes (1927-1991) consists chiefly of correspondence and printed matter from the files of Hildegarde Boughton Forbes (1894-1991). Raised in affluent surroundings, she gamely faced the hardships of a nurse's aide at Fort MacPherson, Georgia during and after the First World War. In 1922 she married Henry Forbes, whose papers are located in Series 3, Subseries 1, and it was at his urging that she formed her connection with the AAIA. Elected to its Board of Directors in 1961, she soon became an influential presence. While she served the Association in a variety of capacities, including as co-chairman of its Ways and Means Committee, and contributed generously to its coffers, it was as its secretary that she left her most indelible mark. Her primary duty in this position, which she occupied from 1964 until failing eyesight compelled her to resign in 1980, was the taking of minutes, both at meetings of the Board of Directors and the Executive Committee. Her handiwork can be found in Series 1, Subseries 1 (Administration).
    The material contained in Forbes' files covers a wide array of matters and constitutes a sort of microcosm of other subseries in the collection during her time of active involvement in the Association. There is a thinness to her files which limit their usefulness, however, though not as an ancillary source of information. The most interesting portion of Forbes' papers is her personal correspondence, documenting, as it does, the AAIA's evolving character and interests and her reactions to these changes. An avid letter writer, she kept in touch with the AAIA's key players from her home in Massachusetts, be it General Counsel Arthur Lazarus, Jr., President Oliver La Farge, or Executive Director William Byler. Forbes' forceful personality emerges clearly in her writing. Self-described as "hard-boiled," she harbored strong opinions and was not afraid to voice them. Her peppery manner could be off-putting, but no one could doubt her dedication to the AAIA. Her underlying warmth of spirit was also palpable when she wrote to President Roger Ernst in 1972, "I was really glad to hear that you are going to a so-called head shrinker. I feel sure that he will -- rather than shrinking -- give you confidence in your own ability, which is great. For several years I was in psychotherapy and wouldn't have missed the experience for anything on earth. Among other things that it did for me was to give me courage to needle 3 Presidents of the AAIA when I saw things going wrong. Now maybe you'll find the courage to hit me over the head when I step out of line."
    The materials in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by subject or last name of correspondent. Formerly restricted material, audio material, and photographs are included at the end of the subseries.
    - Alaska: Correspondence, 1962-1973; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 1)
    - Alaska Council of Churches, 1962; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 2)
    - Alaska: Printed Matter, 1961-1991; 3 folders (Box 388, Folder 3-5)
    - Alcohol and Drug Abuse, 1986; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 6)
    - Alterman, Ruth, 1971-1986; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 7)
    - Amchitka Island Nuclear Test, 1969-1972; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 8)
    - American Indian Arts Center, 1965-1976; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 9)
    - American Indian Trip to China, 1980-1981; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 10)
    - Amory, Cleveland, 1962-1964; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 11)
    - Anderson, Owanah, 1987; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 12)
    - Archaeological Resources Protection Act, 1979; 1 folder (Box 388, Folder 13)
    - Arizona Commission on Indian Affairs, 1972-1979; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 1)
    - Arts and Crafts, 1958-1959; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 2)
    - Baumgartner, Leona, 1964-1978; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 3)
    - Bedford, Jimmy, 1973-1976; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 4)
    - Bennett, Robert, 1966; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 5)
    - Bergen, Alfreda Janis, 1962-1987; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 6)
    - Black Hills Steering Committee, 1987; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 7)
    - Bradford, Penelope, 1979-1980; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 8)
    - Brociner, Phyllis, 1961-1963; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 9)
    - Brooke, Edward W, 1966-1978; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 10)
    - Bruce, Louis R, 1969-1972; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 11)
    - Budget Committee, 1963-1965; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 12)
    - Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1969-1976; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 13)
    - Burke, James A, 1968-1978; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 14)
    - Byler, Mary Lou, 1966-1970; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 15)
    - Byler, William, 1962-1980; 3 folders (Box 389, Folder 16-18)
    - Canada, 1983-1986; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 19)
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1979; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 20)
    - Central Arizona Project, 1980; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 21)
    - Ceremonials and Fiestas, 1964; 1 folder (Box 389, Folder 22)
    - Chavers, Dean, 1987; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 1)
    - Child Welfare, 1968-1988; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 2)
    - Clapp, Winifred, 1965; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 3)
    - Colville Indian Reservation, 1970; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 4)
    - Constitutional Rights, 1961-1968; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 5)
    - Cooke, Alan, 1961-1989; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1991; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 7)
    - Council on Indian Affairs, 1962-1965; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 8)
    - Criminal Justice, 1968-1986; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 9)
    - Dartmouth College, 1966-1971; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 10)
    - Dean, S. Bobo, 1972-1977; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 11)
    - Deloria, Samuel, 1972-1973; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 12)
    - Deloria, Vine, Jr, 1972; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 13)
    - Derogatory Images, 1965-1968; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 14)
    - Donnelly, Brian, 1986; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 15)
    - Dozier, Edward P, 1967-1971; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 16)
    - Dozier, Marianne, 1970-1988; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 17)
    - D-Q University, 1972-1979; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 18)
    - Dukakis, Kitty, 1988; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 19)
    - Dundee, Birdie, 1987; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 20)
    - Echohawk, John E, 1978-1985; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 21)
    - Economic Development, 1969-1986; 1 folder (Box 390, Folder 22)
    - Education, 1963-1976; 1978-1986; 3 folders (Box 391, Folder 1-3)
    - Education Committee, 1966-1982; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 4)
    - Elderly, 1986; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 5)
    - Elias, Nathaniel M, 1962-1964; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 6)
    - Eliot, Abigail A, 1965-1969; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 7)
    - Ely, Gertrude, 1966; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 8)
    - Emergency Jobs Act, 1983; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 9)
    - Ernst, Roger C, 1963-1988; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 10)
    - Everhart, William C, 1976; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 11)
    - Executive Director's Position, undated; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 12)
    - Family Papers, 1934-1981; 1 folder (Box 391, Folder 13)
    - Farley, Edward I, 1969-1971; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 1)
    - Federal Indian Policy, 1953-1985; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 2)
    - Fishing, 1968-1985; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 3)
    - Flannel, Rose, 1963-1971; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 4)
    - Flute, Jerry, 1985-1989; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 5)
    - Forbes, Henry S, 1964; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 6)
    - Force Accounts, 1963; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 7)
    - Fort Hall Shoshone-Bannock, 1961-1962; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 8)
    - Fort Mojave Tribe, 1976; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 9)
    - Four Nation Appeals, 1962-1966; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 10)
    - Fund Raising Appeals, 1962-1965; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 11)
    - Gaming, 1986; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 12)
    - Goldschmidt, Oswald, 1963-1986; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 13)
    - Gordon, Lester E, 1971; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 14)
    - Gramm-Rudman Deficit Reduction Act, 1980; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 15)
    - Gravel, Mike, 1969-1972; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 16)
    - Hale, Thomas Shaw, 1965-1972; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 17)
    - Halfmoon, Richard A, 1974-1980; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 18)
    - Hanley, Joy J, 1988; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 19)
    - Harvard University, 1970-1971; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 20)
    - Hathaway, Stanley K, 1975; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 21)
    - Havasupai Tribe, 1974-1988; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 22)
    - Hawkins, James E, 1963; 1 folder (Box 392, Folder 23)
    - Health, 1955-1973; 2 folders (Box 392, Folder 24-25)
    - Health, 1974-1988; 2 folders (Box 393, Folder 1-2)
    - Hensley, William L, 1978; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 3)
    - Hermelin, Sylvia, 1963-1988; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 4)
    - Heye Foundations, 1964; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 5)
    - Hickel, Walter, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 6)
    - Hirsch, Bertram E, 1978; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 7)
    - Hirschfelder, Arlene B, 1969-1974; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 8)
    - Hitchcock, Kay, 1970-1974; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 9)
    - Hoey, Jane M, 1968; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 10)
    - Hopson, Eben, 1980; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 11)
    - Housing, 1967-1988; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 12)
    - Houston, James and Houston, Alicia, 1972-1975; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 13)
    - Humphrey, Hubert H, 1963-1968; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 14)
    - Indian Community Development Block Grant Program, 1981; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 15)
    - "Indian Country", undated; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 16)
    - Indian Financing Act, 1984; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 17)
    - Indian Judgement Funds, 1973; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 18)
    - Indian Lands, 1963-1982; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 19)
    - Indian Participation Project, 1972; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 20)
    - Indian Resources Development Act, 1967; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 21)
    - Indian Social Services Assistance Act, 1987; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 22)
    - Indian Trust Counsel Authority, 1973; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 23)
    - Indians by Arthur Kopit, 1969; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 24)
    - Inter-American Indian Institute, 1969; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 25)
    - Inter-Cultural Studies Group, 1970-1974; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 26)
    - Inuit Circumpolar Conference and Alaska Native Review Commission, 1983-1986; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 27)
    - Irving, Ella, 1960-1963; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 28)
    - John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, 1982; 1 folder (Box 393, Folder 29)
    - Johnson, Emery A, 1987; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 1)
    - Jones, Audrey, 1972; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 2)
    - Karelsen, Frank E., III, 1967; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 3)
    - Keeler, Frank J, 1962; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 4)
    - Kennedy, Edward M, 1963-1986; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 5)
    - Kimble, Gary N, 1989-1990; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 6)
    - Kress, Francesca, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 7)
    - La Farge, Consuelo, 1970; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 8)
    - La Farge, Oliver, 1958-1963; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 9)
    - Lavin Company, 1965; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 10)
    - Law and Order, 1969; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 11)
    - Lazarus, Arthur, Jr, 1962-1991; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 12)
    - League of Women Voters, 1971; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 13)
    - Legal Defense Committee, 1967; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 14)
    - Lobbying, 1976; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 15)
    - Lowenthal, John, 1978; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 16)
    - McDermott, Walsh, 1981; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 17)
    - McGovern, George, 1963-1976; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 18)
    - McKay, Iliff, 1966-1979; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 19)
    - McLane, Charles M, 1972; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 20)
    - McNickle, D'Arcy, 1971-1977; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 21)
    - Madigan, La Verne, 1957-1962; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 22)
    - Maine Indians, 1961-1986; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 23)
    - Maps, 1972; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 24)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1966; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 25)
    - Meeds, Lloyd, 1977; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 26)
    - "Memories of 90 Years", 1984; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 27)
    - Menominee Indians, 1964; 1 folder (Box 394, Folder 28)
    - Miccosukee Tribe, 1959-1967; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 1)
    - Mitchell, Donald C, 1989-1990; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 2)
    - Mohawk Indians, 1975-1977; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 3)
    - Momaday, Scott, 1964; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 4)
    - Mondale, Walter F, 1989; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 5)
    - Montgomery, Arthur, 1970; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 6)
    - Morgan, Lael, 1988-1990; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 7)
    - Muschenheim, Carl, 1964-1977; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 8)
    - Muschenheim, Ronda, 1961-1989; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 9)
    - Myths and Legends, 1987; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 10)
    - National Council on Indian Opportunity, 1968; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 11)
    - Native American Rights Fund, 1975-1988; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 12)
    - Navajo Indians, 1968-1989; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 13)
    - Newman, Jeffrey, 1969-1974; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 14)
    - Nixon, Richard M, 1968; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 15)
    - Nominating Committee, 1960-1986; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 16)
    - Northern Cheyenne Tribe, 1958-1963; 1 folder (Box 395, Folder 17)
    - Northern Cheyenne Tribe, 1963-1975; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 1)
    - Northwest Office, 1980; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 2)
    - O'Connell, Daniel J, 1969; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 3)
    - Oliver La Farge Fund, 1964-1967; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 4)
    - Ortiz, Alfonso, 1969-1988; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 5)
    - O'Sullivan, Benjamin, 1964-1984; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 6)
    - Peyote, 1951-1960; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 7)
    - Pine Ridge Oglala Sioux Tribe, 1963-1986; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 8)
    - Pollack, Lillian, 1969-1973; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 9)
    - Poole, Rufus, 1969; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 10)
    - Program Against Poverty, 1964-1966; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 11)
    - Program and Budget Committee, 1977-1980; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 12)
    - Program and Operations Committee, 1965; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 13)
    - Proxy Ballot, 1974; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 14)
    - Public Information Activities, 1967; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 15)
    - Public Works, 1962; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 16)
    - Pyramid Lake Paiute Indians, 1967-1985; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 17)
    - Ray, E. Tinsley, 1972-1976; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 18)
    - Reagan Administration, 1980-1987; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 19)
    - Religious Freedom, 1978; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 20)
    - Resnick, Idrian N, 1985-1988; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 21)
    - Rhoades, Everett R, 1972-1986; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 22)
    - Richards, Tom, Jr, 1973-1983; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 23)
    - Road Projects, 1972; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 24)
    - Rock, Howard, 1969-1976; 1 folder (Box 396, Folder 25)
    - Schifter, Richard, 1962-1985; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 1)
    - Scholarships, 1958-1985; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 2)
    - Scientists' Institute for Public Information, 1975; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 3)
    - Self-Determination, 1986; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 4)
    - Simon, John, 1978-1979; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 5)
    - Sisseton-Wahpeton Tribal Health Council, 1967; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 6)
    - Smart, S. Bruce, Jr, 1962-1970; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 7)
    - Smith, Corinna Lindon, 1957-1965; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 8)
    - Social Security, 1968-1972; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 9)
    - Staff, 1972-1978; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 10)
    - Stevens, Alden, 1959-1968; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 11)
    - Stevens, Marion, 1978-1980; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 12)
    - Stevens, Theodore F, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 13)
    - Taos Pueblo Indians, 1964-1974; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 14)
    - Taxation, 1956-1982; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 15)
    - Taylor, Michael N, 1986-1988; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 16)
    - Thompson, Tom, 1987; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 17)
    - Tohono O'odham (Papago), 1986; 1 folder (Box 397, Folder 18)
    - Tribal Agencies Date, 1980; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 1)
    - Tribes, 1958-1987; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 2)
    - Tsongas, Paul E, 1979-1981; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 3)
    - Tundra Times, 1963-1989; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 4)
    - Udall, Stewart L, 1961; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 5)
    - Unger, Steven, 1980-1985; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 6)
    - United Scholarship Service, 1960-1964; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 7)
    - U.S. Senators, 1963-1987; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 8)
    - United Tribes for Reservation Youth, 1985; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 9)
    - Urban Indians, 1970-1971; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 10)
    - Water Rights, 1970-1982; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 11)
    - Watt, James G, 1980-1981; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 12)
    - Ways and Means Committee, 1961-1962; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 13)
    - We Shake Hands, 1957-1963; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 14)
    - Whale Hunting, 1971-1978; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 15)
    - Windsor Alumnae Bulletin, 1968; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 16)
    - Wortis, Ethel E, 1966-1980; 1 folder (Box 398, Folder 17)
    - Wounded Knee Occupation, 1967-1979; 1 folder (Box 399, Folder 1)
    - Youth Conservation Corps and National Service Corps, 1960-1962; 1 folder (Box 399, Folder 2)
    - Youth Employment Act, 1962; 1 folder (Box 399, Folder 3)
    - Material Opened on May 1, 2012, 1962-1982; 1 box (Box 399)
    - Audio Material (Iroquois and Seneca Speakers), 1988; 1 folder (Box 399, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, 1927-1963; 1 box (Box 400)
  - Subseries 3: Oliver La Farge, 1939-1963; 4 boxes
    Series 3: Personal Files, Subseries 3: Oliver La Farge (1939-1963) is largely composed of correspondence and reports relating to La Farge's presidency of the AAIA, an organization with which he was synonymous. La Farge (1901-1963), an anthropologist and Pulitzer Prize winning author, dedicated half his life to the Association and the causes it championed. Born into a cultured New England family, he first encountered Native Americans when, as a student at Harvard University, he accompanied an archaeological expedition to the Navajo reservation. It was a seminal experience. As he would later say, "the Indians got me in 1921." Further trips to the Southwest followed, as did anthropological expeditions to Mexico and Guatemala on behalf of Tulane and Columbia Universities. In 1930 he was elected to the Board of Directors of the Eastern Association on Indian Affairs, as the AAIA was then known, and, in 1933, accepted its presidency. He held this post until his death, with the exception of the years between 1943 and 1948, an interregnum necessitated by his appointment as historical officer for the United States Army's Air Transport Command.
    La Farge's assumption of the Association's presidency in 1933 also saw the adoption of a new name: the National Association on Indian Affairs. It was an appropriate conjunction, for, under his leadership, the Association evolved from a small and precariously situated entity to a vibrant organization with a multidimensional program and a national reach. Despite physical and financial hardships, he strove to better the lives of Native Americans by cultivating understanding, challenging injustice, and answering wants. His deftly written letters demonstrate an acute understanding of human character, and while he was intolerant of the inept and disingenuous, he could exercise great patience and diplomacy. His comprehension of Native Americans was not without limitations, but his commitment to them ran deep. As The New York Times declared on his death, "Oliver La Farge approached the Indian without maudlin sentiment. He liked and respected him, and with gentle but firm good nature he repelled the caricature of the modern Indian as a drunk and a wastrel.... He fought the Indian's battles before many a Congressional committee and White House advisory group. Others were in the fight, too, but it was La Farge's voice that was heard most frequently and most movingly in behalf of the country's original settler."
    The material in this subseries documents La Farge's contribution and that of the AAIA to this struggle during the postwar portion of his presidency -- only a handful of items predate it -- and sheds light on the temperament of this influential figure. Researchers will encounter frank remarks on the AAIA's internal organization, its direction, and its relationship with such entities as the National Congress of American Indians and the Bureau of Indian Affairs. Of particular interest are taut discussions in 1955 concerning the future of Executive Director Alexander Lesser, who, according to La Farge, "is wrecking the association, and no amount of pleading, persuading, or arguing seems to make him see it." Administrative matters form only a part of this subseries, however. It includes substantial files on tribes such as the Navajo and Northern Cheyenne, as well as a collection of field reports containing detailed analyses of Indian communities in various parts of the country. Critical issues confronting Native Americans are also addressed, including the federal government's campaign to terminate its relationship with tribes and its efforts to regulate tribal attorney contracts, thereby limiting the ability of Indians to secure independent counsel. Other files document the AAIA's role in specific battles, such as the vain attempt of the Seneca to halt construction of the Kinzua Dam or the successful efforts of the Pueblo of Taos to secure title to its sacred Blue Lake. This subseries also offers insights into steps the Association took to foster change in public attitudes, a task at which La Farge, wordsmith that he was, excelled.
    The materials in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by type of record (e.g., Field Reports) or subject.
    - Executive Committee, 1954; 1 folder (Box 401, Folder 1)
    - Executive Director's Reports, 1956-1963; 2 folders (Box 401, Folder 2-3)
    - Field Reports, 1959-1962; 2 folders (Box 401, Folder 4-5)
    - Film Committee, 1949-1954; 1 folder (Box 401, Folder 6)
    - Finance, 1952-1954; 1 folder (Box 401, Folder 7)
    - Fund Raising, 1951-1954; 1 folder (Box 401, Folder 8)
    - Health Committee, 1951-1955; 1 folder (Box 401, Folder 9)
    - Iroquois, 1954-1960; 1 folder (Box 401, Folder 10)
    - Legal Committee, 1950-1954; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 1)
    - Legislation, 1954-1956; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 2)
    - Montana Tribes, 1950-1958; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 3)
    - National Congress of American Indians (NCAI) Liaison, 1951-1954; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 4)
    - Navajo, 1949-1955; 2 folders (Box 402, Folder 5-6)
    - Navajo Museum, 1954-1958; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 7)
    - Nebraska Tribes, 1957-1959; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 8)
    - Northern Cheyenne, 1957-1959; 2 folders (Box 402, Folder 9-10)
    - Policy (Including Termination of Federal Responsibilities), 1940-1954; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 11)
    - Program, 1954; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 12)
    - Projects, 1950-1954; 1 folder (Box 402, Folder 13)